陛下
Majesty,
主教大人克朗默觐见
His Grace Archbishop Cranmer is here.
大人
Your Grace.
陛下
Your Majesty...
宣誓效忠陛下为英国教会领袖一事
we have had a great success throughout the whole country
我们已取得了
in the swearing of allegiance to Your Majesty
巨大成功
as Head of the Church.
支持您与安妮王后的婚姻亦是如此
Also in favor of your marriage to Queen Anne.
但我们无法说服
But we cannot persuade either
费施尔或是托马斯·莫尔宣誓
Fisher or Thomas More to swear the oath.
然而… 他们可以对其中的一部分进行宣誓
However... they may swear to part of it.
托马斯爵士已向我们表明
Sir Thomas has already told us he has no
他对继承法案毫无异议 而且…
argument with the Act of Succession,and...
不行
No.
绝不能让步
There can be no compromise.
一旦允许他们如此行事
For if we allow them,of all men,
按照自己的意志宣誓
to swear to what they like,and not anything else,
那么其他人就会有先例可循
then they set a precedent for others to follow.
大人 在此事上
In this matter,Your Grace,
没有回旋余地
it is all or nothing.
谨遵陛下旨意
Majesty.
- 大臣阁下 - 陛下 托马斯爵士之妻艾丽丝夫人
- Mr. Secretary.  - Majesty,Dame Alice,
书信一封
the wife of Sir Thomas has written.
她请求提醒您 她丈夫
She asks to remind you that her husband
长久以来为您效劳
has given long and true service,and
他并无恶意
he does nothing now out of malice,
只是出于自己的良知行事
but only the imperatives of his conscience.
我深知他的良知
I know all about his conscience.
他从不掩饰自己的良知
He's been wearing it on his sleeve for years.
他辞去大法官一职时曾许诺
When he resigned as Chancellor,he made me a great promise
就此不问世事 深居简出
that he would retire from the world and live privately,
潜心修行
and attend his soul.
然而事实并非如此
But this was not true.
他继续书写 刊印有关我的事务
He continued to write and publish pamphlets
有关我道德心的小册子
about my matter and my conscience.
他拜访过凯瑟琳
He visited Katherine.
他笼络其他人支持她
He cajoled others to support her.
换言之 他违背了自己的诺言
In other words,he broke his promise.
他必须承担相应的后果
He must accept the consequences.
陛下
Majesty.
托马斯爵士 有人探访
Sir Thomas,you have visitors.
谢谢
Thank you.
托马斯
Thomas!
玛格丽特 艾丽丝
Margaret! Alice!
看看你…
Look at you...
托马斯·莫尔 我很惊异于你如此一个明智之人
Well,Thomas More,I marvel that you have always been taken
现在的所为却愚蠢不堪
for so wise a man that you will now play
满足于呆在这闭锁 污秽的监狱
the fool here in this close,filthy prison
与鼠辈同处一室
and be content apparently to be shut up among mice and rats.
别这样
Don't be like that!
我保证 这里是
I assure you this is
伦敦塔里条件最好的一间房间
one of the very best rooms in the Tower,
事实上
In fact,
我在形式上为警役的宾客
formally,I am a guest of the Constable,
就是刚刚带你们来的那个人
who just brought you here. And I said to him before
我曾向他表明
that if I showed the least sign
如若我有忘恩负义之举
of ingratitude for his great generosity,
他完全可以把我从塔里扔出去
he should just throw me out of the Tower altogether!
你知道我们为何而来
You know why we have come here.
我以为是来探望我
I thought it was to see me.
是的
Yes.
是为看望你而来
It was to see you.
但除此之外
But beyond that:
请求你宣誓
It was to ask you to swear the oath,
这样我们一家就可以团聚了
so that you can come home with us.
- 艾丽丝 告诉我一件事 - 什么事
- Alice,tell me one thing. - What is that?
这里是否和我自己的房间一样 如此接近天堂？
Is not this house as close to heaven as my own?
好啊 你想说的就是这个吗
Good God,man.Is that all you can say?
你总是这么坦率
You were always plain-speaking,woman.
这就是我钦佩你的地方
It's one of the attributes I admire you for.
那么 恕我直言了 丈夫
Well,then I should tell you plainly,husband,
我 玛格丽特 你所有的家人
that I,and Margaret...and all your other family...
都已经宣过誓
have all sworn the oath
这无伤大雅
and feel no worse for it!
不论男女 我都不会责备宣誓过的人
I have always said that I do not blame any other man
只是我自己难以为之
or woman,who has sworn. I only say that I myself cannot swear.
你就只在乎自己
Then you are thinking only of yourself.
如果你被起诉
If you are proceeded against,
如你所知 所有财产
as you know very well,all your possessions
将收归王室所有
will be forfeited to the Crown.
我们从此会过上拮据的生活
And we would be forced into penury.
我最为忧心的
I have had more sleepless nights
正是此事
over that issue than over anything else.
- 你还是不肯宣誓吗 - 艾丽丝…
- But still you will not swear? - Alice...
我希望你能谅解 求你了 我没有…
I want you to understand,please. I do not...
我并不是自讨苦吃
I do not willingly seek martyrdom.
我会尽我所能
I will do everything I can
迎合国王和他的期望
to accommodate the King and his desires.
我们必须牢记
We must remember that,
他曾向我许诺
he once made me a promise
他永远不会
that he would never
强迫我做违背我良知的事
force me to do anything against my conscience:
上帝居首位
To look first unto God,
其次才是国王
and only after unto him.
玛格丽特 不必悲伤
So,Margaret,don't be sad.
艾丽丝
Alice,
告诉我你没有生气
say you are not angry with me.
求你了
Please.
如果你离开 我带着这个想法
If you left,and I thought so,
会感到自己更加孤立无援
I would feel even more lonely than before.
没有
No.
我并不生你的气
I am not angry with you.
但我被吓坏了
But I am frightened.
惊恐至极
So very frightened.
陛下
Your Majesty.
夫人…
My Lady...
- 怎么回事 - 陛下
- What is it? - Your Majesty.
- 陛下 - 怎么回事
- Your Majesty. - What is it?
上帝啊
My God!
上帝啊…
Oh my God. Oh my God.
快传御医
Get the physician.
我流产了
I lost the baby.
是的
Yes.
他们向我汇报了此事
They told me.
我们不能将真相公之于众
We shall make no public announcement of the fact.
不要
No.
谢陛下恩典
Thank you,Your Majesty.
在此待命 费施尔阁下
Stand by. Mr. Fisher.
我有两个消息通知你
I came to bring you two pieces of news.
首先
In the first place,
教皇已任命你为红衣主教
the Pope has made you a Cardinal...
而坏消息是议会已颁布法令
But the second is that Parliament
恶意否定国王在一切事物上至高无上的权利
has decreed that to maliciously deny the King's supremacy
将视为叛国罪
in all matters,is now a treasonable offence,
处以极刑
punishable by death.
我再问你一遍
So I ask you again:
你是否承认国王
Will you accept the King
为教会领袖
as the Supreme Head of the Church,
并以此宣誓
and take the oath?
你已知我的答复
You already know my answer to that.
我的密探截获了这封信
My agents intercepted this letter.
此信意图向神圣罗马帝国皇帝求援
Its intended recipient was the Emperor.
书信者乞求神圣罗马帝国皇帝
In it,the writer begs the Emperor
侵略英格兰
to invade England and restore
让所谓的王后复位 恢复真理
what he is pleased to call the true Queen and the true faith.
这是你的所为吗
Did you write this letter?
费施尔阁下
In due course, Mr. Fisher,
你到时会因叛国罪接到传讯
you are to be arraigned for treason,
依国王陛下的旨意接受审问
and will be tried according to his Majesty's pleasure.
大臣阁下 感谢你
Mr. Secretary,I must thank you,
将我的冠冕送达
for bringing word of my new hat.
至少不完全是坏消息
At least it was not all bad news.
红衣主教
Cardinal.
大使 请原谅我这般接见你
Forgive me,Ambassador,for receiving you like this.
看到陛下如此情形 我甚感悲伤
I am sad to find Your Majesty so unwell.
何以惊讶
Is it so surprising?
威尔特郡伯爵一干人等
I have received visits from
已到访此地
the Earl of Wiltshire and others,
他们试图说服我宣誓
trying to make me take the oath,
我拒绝之后 便威胁我
and threatening me when I did not.
波林说我必须被送上绞刑台
Boleyn said I should be sent to the scaffold.
我相信那男人绝对是撒旦的使者
I truly believe that man to be an emissary of Satan.
能不能给我说说
Tell me
费施尔主教的消息
what news of poor Bishop Fisher?
国会刚刚通过了新的
Parliament has passed a new
叛国罪法案
Treasons Act
所以"恶意的"否认
which makes "malicious" denial
国王的至尊地位
of the King's supremacy
就可以被判死刑了
punishable by death.
可怜的费施尔
Poor Fisher.
他是护卫我的雄狮
He was a lion in my defense.
如今却要独自死去
Now he will die alone
在监狱中受辱
and ashamed in a prison cell.
怎么会流产的？
What caused it?
没什么特别的事情
There was nothing.
肯定有什么 你做了什么才会流产的？
Of course there was something! What did you do to kill the baby?
我什么也没做
I didn't.
我不知道
I don't know.
相信我 父亲 我一直小心翼翼的
Believe me,father,I was so careful.
但还远远不够
Not careful enough.
从现在开始
Well,from now on
我们必须十分谨慎
we must all be careful,
特别是你
you especially.
要留住国王的宠爱
Not to lose the King's love.
否则一切都将化为乌有
Or everything is lost.
所有的一切
Everything!
为我们所有人着想吧
For all of us!
查尔斯 我想问个问题
Charles. I want to ask you a question.
你睡过的女人中有没有隐瞒
Have any of the women you've bedded ever lied
她不是处女的？
about their virginity?
隐瞒？你应该换过来问
Their virginity? I'd say it's the other way around:
有没有人不隐瞒的？
Did any of them not lie about it?
为什么这么问？
Why do you ask?
我恳求国王陛下的宽恕
I ask Your Majesty's forgiveness.
没关系
It doesn't matter.
我要问的 你说实话就对了
I asked for the truth,and you told me so.
- 那是什么？- 下马
- What's this? - Dismount your horse.
立刻下马
Dismount now!
减速
Down!
早晨好
Good morrow.
- 早晨好 国王陛下 - 你叫什么名字？
- Good morrow,Your Majesty. - What's your name?
威廉·韦伯 陛下
William Webbe,Your Majesty.
不是 我问你宝贝的名字
No,your sweetheart's name?
贝丝 陛下
Bess,Your Majesty.
过来 贝丝
Come here,Bess.
我向陛下保证
I assure Your Majesty
我有许可令 可以
I have a permit and permission
穿越陛下的森林
to ride through Your Majesty's forest.
我发誓是真的 我可以证明
I swear it and could easily prove it.
你好 贝丝
Hello,Bess.
国王陛下
Your Majesty.
跟我来
Come with me.
你真的是英格兰的国王吗
Are you really the King of England?
不是
No.
我只是拖拉你的腿(和你开个玩笑)
I was only pulling your leg.
罗马
ROME
我们来自英格兰的朋友写道
Our English friend writes
"那位女士根本没有怀孕"
that "the Lady is not to have a child after all."
他还提到
He also says that the King
国王早就有出轨的行为了
has already been unfaithful to her,
不过这些都说明不了什么
But all this may mean nothing,
"因为国王多变的性格
"considering the changeable character of the King
和那位女士玩弄他的
and the craft of the Lady,
高超手段"
who well knows how to manage him."
我们俩 坎佩基奥
You and I,Campeggio,
很好地逃离了女人的手段
have done well to avoid the craft of women.
禁欲一劳永逸
Celibacy is an immense relief.
是的 圣父
Yes,Holy Father.
但我们的朋友还是很害怕
But our friend is still fearful
为凯瑟琳王后和他女儿的性命担忧不已
for the lives of Queen Katherine and her daughter.
只要那个情妇掌权一天
Neither of them is safe
他们的性命就受威胁一天
as long as the concubine has power.
我会为我们的姐妹们祈祷
I will have prayers said for our dear sisters
也会为费施尔红衣主教祈祷
and also for Cardinal Fisher.
祈祷上帝能赐予他足够的勇气
May God grant him the courage
来承受即将经历的苦难
to endure his tribulations.
- 是的 圣父 - 另一方面 - 是的？
- Yes,Holy Father. - On the other hand... - Yes?
另一方面
On the other hand,
在教会创立的初期
in the days of the founders of our Church,
殉教被认为是种特权
it was considered a privilege to be martyred,
就像圣·彼得和其他使徒
like St Peter and the other apostles.
我们的教会是在这些殉教者的鲜血下建立起来的
Our Church was founded upon the blood of these martyrs.
所以对于你我来说
So perhaps it is a pity that you and I,
坎佩基奥 不能像费施尔红衣主教那样
Campeggio,unlike Cardinal Fisher,
为耶稣而殉难 是种遗憾啊
no longer have the opportunity to die for Christ.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas...
Sir Thomas!
我在这里
Yes. I'm here.
我在这里 你是谁？
I'm here. Who are you?
约翰 费施尔主教的仆人
John. A servant to Bishop Fisher,
他现在被关在下面
who is kept below here.
他希望你高兴点儿
He asks you to be of good cheer.
他怎么样了？
How is he?
说实话先生 他已年迈 身体也不好
Truth be told,Sir,he is old and not well.
他吃不了这儿的食物
He cannot eat the food here.
但他的意志是坚定不移的
But his spirit remains ever unbroken.
很高兴听你这么说
I am glad to hear it.
而且我一点儿也不惊讶
And not the least bit surprised.
他想知道
He... he asks if you would ever
你会不会考虑发誓…
contemplate taking the oath...
在什么情况下会考虑？
and under what circumstances?
告诉他若我发了誓
Tell him that I cannot take the oath
我的灵魂将受到永世的谴责
without damning my soul for all eternity.
所以我不会发誓的
And that I will not do.
谢谢你 先生
Thank you,Sir,for that;
这肯定能使我的主人为之一振
I know it will renew my master's courage.
现在我必须要走了
Now I must go.
上帝保佑你
God bless you.
告诉我 克伦威尔先生
Tell me,Mr. Cromwell:
托马斯·莫尔还是那么冥顽不灵么？
Does Thomas More still continue in his stubbornness
是的
Yes.
那你必须让他写下不发誓的理由
You will force him to give his reasons for not taking the oath.
否则他的沉默将被认为是别有用意的
Or I will deem his silence on the matter to be malicious.
我任命你为宗教特使
I am appointing you Viceregent in Spiritual Matters.
尽管你是个平信徒而非教士
It's true you are a layman not a churchman
但在这个问题上
but in this matter
我不相信任何教士的偏见
I could not trust the prejudices of any churchman.
夫人 你的姐姐来了
My Lady,your sister has come.
- 妹妹 - 玛莉？
- Sister...  - Mary?
王后陛下
Your Majesty.
你有孩子了？
You are with child!
这怎么回事？我们都不知道
How has it happened? We knew nothing.
我结婚了
I'm married.
结婚了？
Married?
那…
So...
你丈夫是谁？
who is your husband?
他叫威廉·斯塔福德
His name is Mr. William Stafford.
我没听说过 他在宫庭任职吗？
I haven't heard of him. Is he at court?
他…
He...
威廉是个小人物
William is a man of little standing
也没什么钱
and no fortune.
现在他在加来服役
He is now a serving soldier in Calais.
你认为他
Then you think him
配得上
worthy to be the husband
英格兰王后的姐姐？
of the Queen of England's sister?
是的 父亲 因为我爱他…
Yes,father. Since I love him and I
你完全搞错了
You are very much mistaken.
你们私下结婚
You married him in secret,
都没得到我们的允许
and without asking our approval.
像他这种废物我决不会答应的
He is such a nothing we could never have given our permission...
父亲如果你能见见他 你会发现
Father if you were to meet him,you would see
他正直 善良 诚实
that he is a good,fine,honest man.
由于你厚颜无耻的举动 玛莉
Since you acted brazenly and in spite of me,Mary,
我不得不取消对你的年金
I shall cut off your allowance.
我看 你和你善良 诚实的男人
You and your fine,honest young man
就慢慢等死吧
can rot in hell,as far as I am concerned.
安妮…
Anne...
你知道找到一个合适的丈夫
How easy do you think it was for me
对我而言有多困难
to find a proper husband,
因为我一直被称作妓女
when I was called the great prostitute!
遇到威廉 他能爱上我
Indeed I think myself fortunate to have found William,
我一直认为是我天大的福气
and to be loved by him.
你没经过我的允许
You did not ask my permission.
- 我要有你的允许才能爱吗？- 是的
- Do I have to ask your permission to fall in love?  - Yes.
我们现在是皇室成员了
Now we are royalty.
一切不同往昔
Everything is different.
求求你了
Please.
求求你了 妹妹
Please,sister.
不 不行
No. No.
你和你的丈夫将被驱逐出宫
You and your husband are banished from court.
大人
Your Honor,
克伦威尔先生
Mr. Cromwell,
需要我为您做什么吗？
How may I please you?
如果有的话
It would please me very much
就是告诉我
if you could give me the reason or
你不发誓的理由
reasons why you will not take the oath.
我…
I have...
早已把那些事忘得一干二净
discharged my mind of all such matters,
不管是国王还是教皇的头衔 都不关我事
and will no more dispute King's titles,nor Pope's.
若你不给出原因
The King accuses you of stubbornness
国王将以固执而指控予你
and obstinacy,for not giving your reasons.
你必须讲出你对这个法令的看法
You must have some view of the statute?
我认为
I have this view that
国会的这个法案就像
the act of Parliament is like a
一把双刃剑
double-edged sword,
一种回答会使身体受难
for if a man answers one way it confounds his body,
而另一种回答
and if he answers another
将使灵魂受难
it confounds his soul.
但如果你总不表态 会招致惩罚
But by not answering at all,you will incur penalties.
陛下已经命我
His Majesty has commanded me
起草剥夺你的公民权和财产权的议案
to draw up an act of attainder against you.
这将让你在监狱度过下半生
This will make your imprisonment permanent.
可怜的艾丽丝
Poor Alice.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas,
你怎么就不能宣誓呢 很多人都已经接受了
Why will you not take the oath? Thousands have.
我相信其中有许多人和你有同样的信仰
Many,I am sure,share your beliefs and your faith.
但没有你的迟疑
And yet,not your scruples.
至于此 一些人可能是为利益
Well,as for that,some may do it for favor,
另一些人是怕惩罚
and some for fear.
还有一些人可能想着
And some may perhaps think they can
他们日后的悔改能为上帝听到并被宽恕
later repent and be shriven,and God will forgive them.
另一些人会认为如果他们
And some others may be of a mind that if they
说一套 做一套 那么他们即使宣誓
say one thing,but think another,then their oath
也能依据自己的想法做事 而非自己的说法
goes upon what they think and not upon what they say.
但对如此重大的事情我不能那么做
But I cannot use such ways in so great a matter.
这样的话
In which case,
既然你如此诚实
and in all honesty,
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas,
你会付出极大的代价
you are likely to pay the ultimate price.
克伦威尔先生 我们俩其实没什么不同
Mr. Cromwell,there really is no difference between us,
只是我会今日死
except that I shall die today,
而你会明天亡
and you tomorrow.
不好意思 您是玛格丽特·莫尔吗？
Forgive me,but aren't you Margaret More,
托马斯爵士的女儿？
Sir Thomas' daughter?
- 是的 先生 - 我是尤斯塔斯·乔普斯
- Yes,sir. - I am Eustace Chapuys,
王国大使
the Emperor's Ambassador.
能与和托马斯·莫尔爵士有关的人
It is a great pleasure for me to meet
相见 实在是我的荣幸
anyone associated with Thomas More.
谢谢您 阁下
Thank you,Your Excellency.
不知您来宫廷有何贵干？
May I ask why you have come to court?
我是来求克伦威尔大臣阁下的
I have come to petition Mr. Secretary Cromwell.
最近 我们大部分的地被售出
Lately most of our lands have been sold off
我的家族正逐渐穷困下去
and my family is gradually reduced to poverty.
我的母亲正处境艰难
Things go very hard with my mother.
很抱歉你遭遇如此不幸
I am sorry to hear it.
我对这个王国里发生的许多事情感到伤心
I am sorry for many things that are occurring in this kingdom.
好人要受罪
The good seem to suffer,
坏人却逍遥
and the wicked to prosper.
哦 马克
Oh! Mark!
陛下？
Majesty?
你无拘无束 我很喜欢
You're a free spirit. I love that.
其他人都在我面前很拘谨
Everyone else constrains me.
没人理解我
No one understands.
别离开我
Never leave me.
姐姐？
Sister?
我睡不着 不好意思
I couldn't sleep. I'm sorry.
为什么睡不着？
Why could you not sleep?
我在想她的事
I was thinking of her!
谁？
Who?
在想谁的事？
Thinking of who?
当然是玛丽小姐
The Lady Mary,of course.
还有她妈
And her mother!
凯瑟琳
Katherine.
是的 凯瑟琳 你怎么了？
Yes. Katherine! What's wrong with you?
我不明白
I don't understand.
她们还能对你有什么威胁？
What harm can they do you now?
极大的威胁 只要玛丽活着
Every harm! As long as Mary is alive,
她就有可能成为女王
She could be Queen.
不 不会的
No! No,no!
继承法案规定那不可能
The Act of Succession makes it impossible.
伊丽莎白 你女儿
Elizabeth,your daughter
将会继承王位
will be made heir to the throne.
但国王会改变主意
But the King can change his mind!
他现在能随心所欲
He can do whatever he wills now.
他有绝对权利 你知道的
He has absolute power. You know that!
他赐予的
And what he has given,
他能拿走
he can take away,
而被他拿走的又能被再次赐予
and what taken away,he can give back.
他可以继续授予玛丽女王
And he could still make Mary Queen,
甚至在我女儿之上
even above my daughter.
- 可他干嘛那么做？- 我不知道
- But why should he?  - I don't know.
我只是怕那会发生
I just fear it.
这是我对玛丽的理解
This is all I know of Mary
不是我置她于死地
that she is my death,
就是我被她所杀
and I am hers!
我们祖宗的天主
Benedicant te,Domine,
只有你配得赞美
omnes angeli et santi tui.
你的名号是世世代代应受颂扬的
Benedicant te caeli,terra,mare,
诸天及你的一切造物
et omnia quae in eis sunt.
都应赞颂你于无穷之世
In te speravi,Domine:
是你创造了…
Tu es Deus meus.
托马斯
Thomas!
- … 托马斯爵士 - 约翰…
- ...Sir Thomas! - John...
是你吗 约翰？
Is that you,John?
我的主人 费舍尔主教被判决有罪
My master,Cardinal Fisher,is found guilty
并将在明天被执行
and is called forth tomorrow.
他希望你和他能尽早在天堂相会
He hopes you and he shall soon meet in heaven.
告诉他一定如此
Tell him that will be the way,
因为我们殊途同归
for it is a very strait gate we are in.
约翰…
John...
约翰… 告诉他
John... tell him
他配得上并将会得到
he deserves and will receive
- 所有来自天堂的祝福 - 是 先生
- all of heaven's graces. - Yes sir.
愿主保佑您 先生
God bless you,sir.
愿主保佑你
God bless you.
以圣父 圣子 及圣灵之名
In nomine Patris et Filii et Spiritus Sancti.
你看见了 我穿来了最好的衣服
You see that I am wearing my finest clothes,
因为今天是我大喜的日子
for today is my wedding day!
子民们
Good people,
我恳求你们爱戴吾王并跟随他
I ask you to love the King and obey him,
因为他本质不坏…
for he is good by nature...
即使他的宗教政策并不正确
even if he is not right in his religious policies.
但我却因希望维护
But I am condemned to die for wishing to uphold
上帝及宗座的荣耀而被处刑…
the honor of God and the Holy See...
现在 我的天主子民们
And now,good Christian people,
我请求你们的祈祷
I ask for your prayers.
我只是具肉身
I am only flesh,
和任何人一样都怕死
and fear death as much as any man.
我的确是
It's true that I have
早就做好了赴死的准备
long since made up my mind to die,
如果需要我为耶稣和他的教会殉教…
if need be,for Christ and His Church...
但现在 死亡时刻已经到来
But now that the moment is at hand,
我需要你们的帮助
I need your help.
上帝保佑您 费舍尔红衣主教
God bless you,Cardinal Fisher.
上帝保佑您
God bless you.
不像那个混蛋
Not like that asshole!
摩西画的看起来就像是堆垃圾
Moses looks like a pile of crap
- 圣父 - 你知道那是谁吗？
- Holy Father! - Do you know who that was?
不知道
No.
米开朗琪罗·路多维可·利奥纳多·博那罗蒂·西蒙尼
Michelagniolo di Ludovico di Lionardo di Buonnarroti Simoni.
米开朗琪罗？是他？
Michelangelo? That was him?
是他 我们原谅他
That was him. We forgive him
因为他是个天才…
Because he is a genius...
不管那意味着什么
Whatever that means.
教皇陛下 我们从英格兰得到消息
Holiness,we have heard from England
费施尔主教已被谋杀
of the murder of Cardinal Fisher.
他的头被利斧砍下
His head was struck from his body with an axe.
我已经听说了 这是一起暴行
I have already heard. It is an outrage.
我已追封费施尔为教会亲王…
I had made Fisher a Prince of the Church...
但这对亨利国王毫无意义
but it mattered nothing to King Henry,
他现在已恶习缠身
who is now so mired in vice
欲望不止 他已经失去理智了
and lust that he is beyond reason.
陛下 既然费施尔已经死了
Majesty,now that Fisher is dead,
该怎么处置莫尔？
what is to be done about More?
继续施压 克伦威尔先生
We should press ahead,Mr. Cromwell.
继续施压
We should press ahead.
父亲 这里发生了什么？
Father,what has happened here?
我觉得他们对你不如以前了
It seems to me that they are treating you worse than before.
他们拿走了我的炉子
Well,they've taken my stove,
和一些衣服
some clothing.
我的食物供给减少了
My food is reduced.
父亲 现在你还要怎么…
Father how can you...
玛格丽特
Margaret,
你一定不要为我担心
you must not be concerned about me.
我已经冥思了很久
I've thought long and hard
关于基督的受难和死亡…
about Christ's Passion and pain and...
我不惧怕死亡
I am not afraid of death.
我只怕受刑
I am only afraid of torture.
如果他们用暴力让我屈服
If they use violent ways to make me swear.
我不知道我能有多勇敢
I don't know how brave I would be.
但你不用遭受任何苦难
But you do not have to suffer anything.
宣誓就是了…
Just take the oath...
就像我一样
like I did.
就像其他人一样
Like everyone has done.
只要说出它 你会获得自由
Just say it; and your body will be saved.
但我要出卖灵魂才能获得自由
But the saving of my body,will be at the expense of my soul.
- 不是 - 是的
- No!  - Yes.
不是的 我们都不相信那些话
No. None of us believes that.
父亲 求你
Father,please.
求你…
Please...
看在你爱我们的份上
For the love I know you bear us,
别这么做
don't do this to us.
大臣先生
Mr. Secretary...
理查德·瑞奇爵士
Sir Richard Rich.
理查德爵士…
Sir Richard...
很高兴能见到你
I'm very pleased to see you.
我给你个事儿做
I have a job for you.
为什么？
Why?
为什么他就不能像别人一样？
Why can he not be like others?
他为什么要和我对着干？
Why does he have to cross me?
为什么他比国王还要自负？
Why can his vanity be greater than a king's?
这困扰着我
It troubles me.
它占据着我的意识
It ways on my conscience and my heart
我的心又劳累又悲伤
is full and heavy and sore.
我只对你说这些 只对你坦白这些
I say this only to you. I confess only to you.
我欣赏他
I love him.
也憎恶他
And I hate him.
我的恨和爱一样多
I hate in equal measure to my love,
因为他否定我
for he is the spirit that denies.
这取决与您的裁决
It is up to you to judge,
他到底会不会使我良心难安
whether or not,he be on my conscience!
理查德爵士
Sir Richard.
日安
Good day to you.
我看我的牢房快成了律师会面室
I see my cell is fast becoming the place for lawyers to meet.
对不起… 托马斯
I am afraid,Thomas,
我很不情愿的奉命来此
that I come here most unwillingly for I am ordered to
没收你的所有书籍和纸张
deprive you of all your books and papers...
诸如此类
and suchlike.
真可惜
That is a pity.
既然 你奉命前来 我想
Still,if you are ordered to,I suppose,
我想别无选择
then I suppose there is no other way.
你最好开始吧
You had best get started.
能问个问题吗 托马斯
May I ask you a question,Thomas?
只能是假设性的问题 理查德
Only if it's a hypothetical one,Richard.
- 那样比较好 - 假设
- It's better that way.  - Suppose,then,
国会颁布了一项法令
that Parliament enacted a bill
宣布我 理查德·瑞奇为国王
to say that I,Richard Rich,was King,
否认的人将视为叛国者
and that it would be treason to deny it...
你会接受我为国王吗
would you accept me as King?
会
Yes.
但是让我用另一个假设来回答
But let me counter with another hypothetical case:
假设国会颁布法案宣布
Suppose Parliament enacted that.
上帝不存在
God's not God,
不承认即视为叛国者
and to oppose the act would be treason,
你会承认上帝不存在吗
would you say that God was not God?
不会 因为国会无法制定这样的法律
No. Since no parliament can make any such law.
他们没有资格决定上帝是否存在
It has no competence to decide on the existence of God.
国会也就没有资格决定国王
And no more can Parliament make the King
能否成为教会的最高领袖
Supreme Head of the Church!
那好 托马斯
There,Thomas.
我想我的差事做完了
I think my work here is done.
王后陛下 国王驾到
Your Majesty,the King is here.
我的夫人
My Lady.
来这边
Come here.
你对我是否还有激情？
Do you still have a passion for me?
是的 亲爱的
I do,sweetheart.
我爱你
I love you.
现在 别哭了
There now. Don't weep.
别哭泣 我心爱的女人
Don't weep,my own darling.
会好的
It's all right.
一切都会好的
Everything is going to be all right.
威斯敏斯特
Westminster
托马斯·莫尔爵士 你将在这个委员会前
Sir Thomas More,you are arraigned before this commission
以叛国罪名接受公诉
on charges of high treason.
你对此项指控如何回答？
How do you answer the charges?
首先我要否认
Let me begin by denying
我从未恶意反对
that I ever maliciously opposed
国王与安妮·博林的婚姻
the King's marriage to Anne Boleyn.
我从未对此发表恶意言论
I have never spoken maliciously against it...
有且也仅限于我的想法
but only sometimes according to my mind,
意见与良知
opinion and my conscience...
并因此遭受痛苦
and have suffered as a result.
但你恶意否认了《至尊法案》
But you have maliciously denied the Act of Supremacy!
不 我一直对此沉默
No. I have been silent upon it.
对我的缄默而言 不管是你们的法律
And for all my taciturnity neither your law
还是世上任何一部法律
nor any law in the world is
都无法因此公正合法的问刑于我
able, justly and rightly, to condemn me,
除非你有我确凿的
unless you may also lay to my charge
语言或行为
either some word or some deed.
你的沉默也可视为一种行为
Your silence can easily be construed as an action.
即使在此情形下
Ah,but even in that case,
沉默的约定俗成定义
the presumption that silence gives consent
恰恰能让对我的指控无效
precludes the charge against me:
[拉丁语]沉默 即为默许
"Qui tacet,consentire videtur."
对指控
What of the charge that,
你与费施尔主教同谋谋反的罪名有何回应？
you conspired in prison with Bishop Fisher a convicted traitor?
我在狱中从未见过他
I never met him in prison.
我和他的仆人也只有只言片语
I only talked a little with his servant
家常话或勉励而已
about familiar things and recommendations,
因为我们相识已久
such as were seemly to our long acquaintance.
我们回到你假定沉默
We go back to your supposed silence
与《至尊法令》的指控上来
on the Act of Supremacy.
我们认为你就此的确发表过言论
We think you have in fact spoken about it.
我们有目击证人
And we have a witness.
传副总检察长
Call the solicitor general.
传理查德·瑞奇先生
Call,Mr. Richard Rich.
理查德 你已立誓
Richard,you are under oath.
你能否坦诚的告诉本委员会
Do you tell this commission,truthfully,
- 被告到底对你说过什么？- 是的 大人
- what the accused said to you on this matter. - Yes,sirs.
我们都同意国会不能
We agreed that Parliament might not make
制定否认上帝存在的法律
any such law that God was not God.
就此事托马斯爵士说道
To which Sir Thomas said:
"国会也同样不能确立
"No more could Parliament make
国王为教会的最高领袖"
the king Supreme Head of the Church."
这么说他恶意否认了国王的权威？
So he maliciously denied the King's authority?
- 这些是原话？- 是的 大人
- In those words?  - Yes,sir.
字字属实
In those exact words.
我将负责本委员会相应裁决
Then I will charge this commission to return a true verdict.
我请诸位大人一起裁定是否托马斯·莫尔爵士
I ask you,good sirs,to determine whether Sir Thomas More
在与理查德·瑞奇爵士
did converse with Sir Richard Rich
的对话中发表了主张性的言论
in the manner alleged?
你们也认为他有罪吗
You do so find him guilty?
既然如此 我将对犯人进行宣判
Then I will proceed in judgement against the prisoner.
法官大人 当我做律师时
My Lord,when I was a lawyer,
法庭惯例是在判决前
the convention was to ask the prisoner
先由犯人
before judgement was given,
为自己做最后的辩护
why judgement should not be given against him.
那么好吧 你可为自己辩护
What,then,are you able to say to the contrary?
谢谢
Thank you.
依我之见
To my view,
这项控告
this indictment is
是基于一项直接对立
grounded upon an act of Parliament
于上帝律法和其神圣教会的法案
directly repugnant to the laws of God and His Holy Church,
其最高领袖地位不可
the supreme governance of which
由任何世俗君王自行以任何法律形式自封
no temporal prince may presume by any law to take unto himself.
它属于… 它属于
It belongs... It belongs
它只合法属于罗马教廷
by right to the See of Rome,
圣彼得和他的继任者们
to St Peter and his successors...
此乃救世主在世时的亲口教诲
as our Saviour told us Himself when He was on earth!
这个王国 作为教会延伸的一小部分
This realm,being but one small part of the Church,
不可制定任何特别法律 抵触
cannot make any particular law, disagreeable to the
基督律法与普世天主教会
general laws of Christ's universal Catholic Church.
不可…
No more...
英格兰王国不可拒绝服从罗马教廷
No more can this realm of England refuse obedience to Rome
就如同生子不可不认其生父
than can a child refuse obedience to his own natural father...
我们现在明白无误地看清你的恶意倾向
We now plainly see that you are maliciously bent.
不 大人们 绝无恶意
No,sirs. Not maliciously.
但愿我们今后都能在天堂快乐的相遇
I hope we may all meet merrily in heaven hereafter...
我祈求全能的上帝
and I desire Almighty God to preserve and
保佑国王陛下
defend the King's Majesty,
为他遣来忠臣良言
and to send him good counsel.
托马斯·莫尔爵士
Sir Thomas More,
你将被绑在囚笼
you are to be drawn on a hurdle
拖过全伦敦城到泰柏恩行刑场
through the City of London to Tyburn,
在刑场上吊到半死之后
there to be hanged till you be half dead,
趁没断气前从绳索上
after that cut down alive,
挖出你的肚肠撕下你的心肺
your bowels to be taken out of your body
在你面前烧掉
and burned before you,
割去你的生殖器
your privy parts cut off,
砍掉你的头颅
your head cut off,
将你的身体肢解成4段…
your body to be divided in four parts...
父亲 请保佑我们 父亲
Father, bless us, father.
我保佑你们 我的孩子们 振作起来
I bless you,my children. Be of good cheer,
我祈祷在天堂中与你们重逢
for I pray that we will meet together in heaven...
何时行刑？
When is the execution?
明天 陛下
Tomorrow,Your Majesty.
明天几号？
What date is that?
7月6日
The 6th of July.
几时？
What time?
上午10点
At ten in the morning.
我决定将判决减刑为砍头
I have decided to commute the sentence to beheading.
谕令行刑官
Tell the officials.
是 陛下
Yes,Your Majesty.
出于怜悯 我们恳求主
Pietate tua,quaessumus Domine,
免除我们的罪责
nostrorum solve vincula peccatorum.
奉童贞圣母玛利亚之名
Et intercedente beata Maria semper virgine.
让我们永做您忠实的仆人
Nos famulos tuos in omni sanctitate custodi.
因主耶稣基督之名
Per Christum Dominum nostrum.
谢谢 汉弗莱爵士
Thank you, Sir Humphrey.
不过我再跌倒的话
But when I come down again,
让我自行处理吧 随其自然
let me shift for myself,as well as I can.
我请求你们为我作证
I ask you to bear witness with me
我即将从容就死
that I shall now suffer death in
殉教于神圣的天主教会的信仰
and for the faith of the Holy Catholic Church.
我诚挚地乞求你们为国王祈祷
I beg you earnestly to pray for the King,
并转告他
and tell him
我死也是他的忠诚仆从
I died his good servant
但我首先服从上帝
but God's first.
我恳求您的原谅和祝愿
I ask for your pardon and blessing.
今天你将给我以任何凡夫俗子
You will give me this day a greater benefit than any mortal man
都无法给予的恩惠
can ever be able to give me.
鼓起勇气 伙计
Pluck up your spirits,man,
不必惧怕履行自己的职责
and be not afraid to do your office.
求主怜悯 恳求您的宽恕
Miserere miti Domime,secundum miseration un tuum.